Not too long ago, on a cold winter night, there was a teenager who wanted more screen time and a parent who said no.
不久前的一个寒冷冬夜，一个青少年想多玩一会儿手机，家长不同意。
The teenager was advocating for her right to scroll for an extra 30 minutes.
这个青少年力争自己有权再多刷30分钟屏幕。
The parent argued that none of her friends’ parents let them have screens after 9 o’clock.
家长争辩说，她朋友的父母都不允许孩子晚上9点以后看屏幕。
“I thought, in this family, we don’t compare ourselves with other people, Dad?” the teenager replied.
“爸爸，我以为在我们家，我们不和别人比较呢？”青少年回答说。
The parent — who was me, by the way — just got served.
那位家长——顺便说一句，就是我——被将了一军。
Since they were young, I have told my kids not to compare themselves with other people.
从孩子们很小的时候起，我就告诉他们不要和别人比较。
I have argued countless times that comparisons are the “thief of joy”.
我无数次地说过，比较是“快乐的窃贼”。
Although my daughter didn’t win, she did help expose one of the worst pieces of advice I have ever given.
虽然我女儿没有赢，但她确实帮我揭露了我给过的最糟糕的建议之一。
In my defence, I did what we’ve all done before, which is repeat received wisdom without exploring the nuances.
为我自己辩解一句，我做了我们大家以前都做过的事，那就是重复人们普遍接受的观点，而没有去探究其中的细微差别。
But now is the time to set the record straight, which starts with questioning the idea that all social comparison is unhealthy.
但现在是时候澄清事实了，首先就要质疑“所有社会比较都是不健康的”这一观点。
Social comparisons do, of course, often get us into emotional trouble.
当然，社会比较确实常常让我们陷入情绪困扰。
But they can be harnessed for our betterment if we understand how they work.
但如果我们了解它们的运作方式，就可以利用它们来让自己变得更好。
The social comparisons we make — ones that lead us to feel good or bad about ourselves — are vital to our ability to thrive.
我们所做的社会比较——那些让我们自我感觉良好或糟糕的比较——对我们成长发展的能力至关重要。
Science provides a guide we can use to harness the way we perform these comparisons to reduce their negative emotional impacts.
科学提供了一份指南，我们可以用它来驾驭自己进行比较的方式，从而减少比较带来的负面情绪影响。
Comparing yourself with someone who is outperforming you could result in feelings of envy if you focus on the things they have and you don’t, or it can be energizing and inspiring if you use these comparisons as a source of motivation, for example, “If they can achieve that, so can I.”
和比你表现更好的人比较，如果你只盯着他们有而你没有的东西，就可能产生嫉妒；但如果你把这种比较当作动力来源，比如“他们能做到，我也能”，它就能让你充满干劲、受到鼓舞。
Comparing yourself with someone who is doing worse than you could result in fear and worry if you think about how you could fall into similar circumstances, or it can draw out feelings of gratitude and appreciation if you use that comparison to broaden your views — for example, “Wow, things could be much worse; I’m doing great.”
和比你境况更差的人比较，如果你去想自己会不会也落入类似的处境，就可能产生恐惧和担忧；但如果你借这种比较开阔视野，比如“哇，情况本可能糟得多，我已经过得很好了”，它就能唤起感激和感恩之情。
What I wish I taught my daughter earlier are these nuances.
我真希望当初早点教给女儿的，正是这些细微之处。
How we feel about ourselves rests not just on whom we compare ourselves with but also on how we think about that comparison.
我们如何看待自己，不仅取决于我们和谁比较，还取决于我们如何看待这种比较。
That’s something we all have control over.
这是我们每个人都能掌控的。